Sarah Leonard Combe Collection
Sarah Leonard Combe Collection
1861-1979
1861-1868
1 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings, memorabilia pertaining to the American Civil War.
5012985
Biographical History
Nothing is known of Sarah Leonard Combe other than what can be gleaned from the collection. She resided in Syracuse with her husband Hamilton R. Combe. Hamilton Combe served in the 12th New York as first lieutenant (May 12 to October 22, 1861) and then as captain (October 22, 1861, to October 27, 1862). An"Aunt Hannah" is mentioned but, it's uncertain whether she was Sarah's aunt by blood or by marriage.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Sarah Leonard Combe Collection consists of correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence contains military items connected with Company J of the New York Militia, stationed at Fort Tillinghast (near Washington, D.C.) between 1861 and 1862, and more than one hundred letters from Sarah Leonard Combe of Syracuse, New York, to her husband, Hamilton R. Combe, a lieutenant and then captain of Company J. Transcriptions were donated with the collection and are foldered at the end of each year; these have not been checked for accuracy.
There is also a flash drive containing electronic versions of the transcriptions.
Memorabilia contains a few newspaper clippings from the Syracuse, New York area, a photograph of an unidentified family group, and a printed lottery advertisement.
Writings contains Sarah Combe's diary for 1862, an essay by her on "The Future," and a biographical sketch of her written in 1979. Transcriptions of the diary and essay were donated with the collection and are foldered at the end of each year; these have not been checked for accuracy.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Civil War (U.S.); Military history; New York State; Women Authors; Combe, Hamilton R.; Combe, Sarah Leonard.; New York (State). -- Militia. -- Regiment, 12th.; Soldiers -- New York (State); Women -- Diaries.; Women -- New York (State) -- Social life and customs.; Fort Tillinghast (Arlington, Va.); Syracuse (N.Y.) -- History.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; USB flash drives.; Military records.; Photographs.; Transcripts.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alicia L. Watson, 2017.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - List of letters, by date (Box 1)
  - Military items, Company J, 12th New York Volunteers, 1861-1862; includes muster roll for April to June of 1862, list of men engaged in the battle at Gaines's Mill (also known as the First Battle of Cold Harbor or the Battle of Chickahominy River); with transcripts; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1861; with transcripts; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1862; with transcripts; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1863; with transcripts; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1864; with transcripts; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1865; with transcripts; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - [General], 1866-1868; includes transcripts; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - [General], undated; with transcripts; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Flash drive, combe_sl_001; contains electronic versions of lists (Excel) and transcripts (Word) mentioned above and in Writings below (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1850; 1911,; undated (Box 2)
  - Lottery, undated; printed ad for lottery sponsored by a Baltimore, Maryland jewelry company (Box 2)
  - Photograph, undated; unidentified family portrait (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Diary, Sarah Combe, 1862; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Small black leather-bound volume embossed with "DIARY 1862" in gold. An entry from 1 Nov 1862 reads, "To-day my heart was made glad by the unexpected return of my dear H., who says he is done soldiering and come to stay with me." At the back is a section of "Cash Accounts" pages. The second folder contains a full transcript.
  - Essay, "The Future" by Sarah Combe, undated; with transcript (Box 2)
  - "Sarah Leonard Combe: A Victorian Woman" by Alicia Lathrop Kirkland, 16 Dec 1979; typed, 21pp; includes photograph of a portrait of Sarah Combe (Box 2)